Guide to the Rolland and Lottie Welch Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Rolland and Lottie Welch Papers
1900-1970
1917-1923
RG 224
Yale University Divinity School Library
6
(7 boxes)
The work of medical missionary Rolland Welch and his wife Lottie in Hunan, China from 1917 to 1923 is documented by letters, writings, photographs, lantern slides, printed material, and memorabilia.
Welch, Rolland
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mabel Welch Schroeder, 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
Rolland Aretus Welch was born on November 16, 1884 in Shepherd, Michigan, the son of Russell and Isabella Asenath Welch. He attended public schools and graduated in 1908 from Spring Arbor Seminary, an academy founded by leaders of the Free Methodist Church. Rolland then trained for one year at the American Missionary Medical College before beginning work at the Battle Creek Sanitarium in Michigan. Raised in a religious family, Rolland became a professing Christian at age ten, Sunday School Superintendent by age fourteen, and a licensed preacher by age seventeen.
Lottie Belle McClain was born April 23, 1885 in Centerville, Michigan, the daughter of Reuben and Clementine Carr McClain. Her mother died when she was a toddler so her father's brother and wife (William McClain) raised her. Her aunt died when she was thirteen years old and she lived with her cousin before going to work in the paper mills in Three Rivers, Michigan. In order to be closer to work, she found a room with Will and Mary Bridgman, who provided a family relationship for her in future years. Lottie moved to Battle Creek, Michigan in 1902. She became a Christian in 1904 and united with the Free Methodist Church in 1904. She began nurses training a the Battle Creek Sanitarium in 1907, where she met Rolland Welch.
Rolland and Lottie married on August 19, 1909. The couple went to Washington, Kansas where Rolland served as a minister for one year. They returned to Battle Creek in August 1910. Their first child, Rolland William, was born on September 9, 1912 but lived for only ten days, due to injuries related to birth trauma. Their daughter, Mabel, was born on May 31, 1914. Rolland resumed his medical training at the University of Illinois, into which the American Missionary Medical College had merged, and received his M.D. in 1915. Rolland worked as a physician and surgeon at the Battle Creek Sanitarium until April, 1917, when he was appointed as a medical missionary under the United Evangelical Mission. The United Evangelical Church was created in 1891 when some members of the Evangelical Association, also known as the Albright Brethren, left to form the new church. In 1922 the two groups reunited in Detroit and renamed themselves "The Evangelical Church."
Lottie completed the "First Standard Teacher Training Course" given by the Teacher Training Board of the Free Methodist Church in May 1917 but required additional education in order to join the United Evangelical Mission in China. After Rolland sailed for China, Lottie and Mabel remained in Greenville, Illinois where she attend the Greenville College Preparatory School, graduating in June 1918. Lottie and Mabel sailed for China in September, 1918. They remained in Nanking for a few months for language study before joining Rolland because women and children were not allowed to go Yuhsien at that time, due to war conditions. During the summer months Lottie and Mabel lived at the missionary resort in Kuling. Rolland was Superintendent of Emma Dubs Memorial Hospital in Yuhsien, Hunan province until 1923. The Emma Dubs Memorial Hospital was built in 1919-1920 under the direction of Rev. C.C. Talbott and Dr. Rolland Welch, who had earlier opened a dispensary in Yuhsien.
Rolland suffered from acute ill health in late 1922 and early 1923 and the Welches returned to the U.S. for furlough in the fall of that year. They had expected to return to China, but were not reappointed by the mission board. Rolland practiced medicine in Bellevue, Michigan from 1924 until his death in 1934.
Scope and Contents
Though the Welches were missionaries in China for a relatively brief time, this collection provides valuable documentation about their missionary experience, the development and operations of a hospital in Hunan Province, and the work of the United Evangelical Mission (later known as the Evangelical Mission). Letters exchanged between Rolland and Lottie during the times of separation when Lottie was in the U.S., Nanking, or at the missionary resort of Kuling provide interesting detail regarding their daily life. Relationships established with both missionary and Chinese colleagues remained influential in the Welches' lives well after their return from China. Their own letters and the letters that the Welches received from missionary colleagues in China after their return to the U.S. in 1923 describe political unrest, banditry, tension within the mission, and the medical work of the mission.
Included in the collection is a set of lantern slides, with descriptions, which were used by Rolland Welch to give presentations about the China mission in churches in the U.S. following their return.
Some documents in the collection are photocopies or scans made from albums that had been compiled by the donor. The original albums were returned to the donor. The photocopies have been integrated into the chronological or alphabetical sequence of the series into which they fit.
Arrangement
I. Family Correspondence, 1917-1925
II. General Correspondence, 1914-1970
III. Biographical Documentation, 1917-1923
IV. Photographs and Lantern Slides, 1917-1923, n.d.
V. Collected Material and Memorabilia 1900-1947, n.d.
Missions -- China; Missionaries, Medical -- China; Missionaries; Welch, Rolland; Welch, Lottie McClain; United Evangelical Church -- Missions
- Family Correspondence, 1917-1925; Series I
  - Rolland to Lottie
    - Enroute to China, 1917 Apr-May (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - From China, 1917 Jun-Jul (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - From Yuhsien, 1917 Aug - 1918 Mar (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
    - From Yuhsien and Kuling, 1918 Apr-Jun (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - From Kuling, anticipating the arrival of Lottie and Mabel from the U.S., 1918 Jul-Sep (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - From Yuhsien, to Lottie and Mabel in Nanking, 1918 Oct-Nov (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - From Yuhsien; from trip to Peking where he attended a medical conference, 1920 Feb - Jun (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - From Yuhsien, 1920 Jul (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - From Yuhsien to Lottie and Mabel in Nanking; from visit to Dr. Dubs in Liling and from Shanghai to Lottie and Mabel in Yuhsien, 1920 Aug- Nov (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - From Hankow and Peking to Lottie and Mabel in Yuhsien; from Yuhsien to Lottie and Mabel in Kuling, 1921 Feb-Jun (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - From Yuhsien to Lottie and Mabel in Kuling, 1922 May-Sep (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Family back in the U.S.; from Bellevue, Michigan and Chicago, 1924 Jul, 1925 Jul (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Lottie to Rolland
    - From Greenville, IL to Rolland in China., 1917 May-1918 Jul (Box 1, Folder 15-20)
      Scope and Contents
      Lottie was taking courses, graduating in June 1918
    - From Nanking, 1918 Nov-Dec (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Lottie was attending Language School
    - From Kuling, 1919 Jun-Sep (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - From Kuling, 1920 May-Aug (Box 1, Folder 23-25)
    - From Yuhsien to Rolland in Liling and Shanghai, 1920 Oct-Nov (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - From Kuling, 1921 May-Jun (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - From Kuling, 1922 Jun-Sep (Box 1, Folder 28)
- General Correspondence, 1914-1970; Series II
  - Letters to be read by Rolland during voyage to China from colleagues and friends in the U.S, 1917 Apr (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
  - Mr. and Mrs. H. C. Anderson to the Welches in the U.S., primarily from Yuhsien, 1924 Apr- 1927 Mar (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Including regarding the sale and shipment of the Welches belongings and tensions within the mission community
  - To Lottie from Jennie Armstrong, a friend in Illinois, 1918 Dec- 1924 May (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - B, 1918-1922 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Lottie to the Bridgman family, from Nanking, Yuhsien, and Kuling, 1918 Oct-1920 Dec (Box 2, Folder 34)
    The Bridgmans acted as family for Lottie, including providing supplies for the Welches in China and doing financial transactions.
  - Lottie and Mabel to/from the Bridgman family, 1921 Jan-1923 Oct (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Including Lottie's commentary on missionary work
  - To Welches from A.H. and Lora Butzbach, primarily written from Kuling, 1923 Oct -1926 Apr (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Including regarding bandits and kidnapping, and mission affairs
  - C, 1923-1924 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    Including from Teofile Corpus, District Health Officer, Philippines, and from missionary colleagues in China
  - To Welches from Cowles family, 1925 Jul -1965 Dec (Box 2, Folder 37a)
  - To Welches from Mabel Cook, 1918 Sep-1924 Apr (Box 2, Folder 38)
    Mabel Cook was the office secretary of the General Missionary Board of the Free Methodist Church, to which the Welches owed some money.
  - To Welches from Chinese students, 1922 Sep-1930 Mar (Box 2, Folder 39-40)
  - To Welches from Homer and C. Dubs, 1917 Apr-1918 Nov (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - To Lottie from Iva Dunlap, 1923-1925, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 42)
    Iva Dunlap taught at the Evangelical Mission in Changsha; letters include information about woman and girl apparently supported by Lottie
  - E-G, 1917-1924 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    Including from G. Epp, Executive Secretary-Treasurer of the Missionary Society of the Evangelical Church re. childrens' allowance and medical bill.
  - To Welches from Hang family, 1924 May-1926 Jun (Box 2, Folder 44)
    The Hang family were friends and co-workers with the Welches in Yuhsien. Mr. Hang was the principal of the Le Teh Boy's Middle School. The letters describe loss of trust in the staff of the Emma M. Dubs Memorial Hospital and unrest in the school population because of anti-missionary propaganda in the period after the Welches left China.
  - To Welches from Heidenreich family, 1918 Jul-1926 Oct (Box 2, Folder 45)
    Including from Elsie Heidenreich, missionary in Yuhsien and Kuling
  - To Lottie from Mrs. Robert Hess, a friend from Woodbine, IL, 1918 Jul-1924 Jan (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - To Lottie from Cora Hobein, primarily written from Yuhsien and Changsha, 1918 Sep-1926 Dec (Box 2, Folder 47)
    Cora Hobein worked at the Emma Dubs Memorial Hospital. Her letters describe the ongoing mission work as well as soldiers and bandits in the area.
  - To Welches from Hoffman and Hubly, 1920-1925 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - To Welches from Rose Holtzman, a friend in Illinois, 191 Jan-1925 Jul (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - To Welches from Jespersons, Battle Creek Sanitarium, 1922 Jan (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - To Welches from D.R. and Martha Kauffman, 1919 Dec-1927 Jan (Box 2, Folder 51)
    The Kauffmans served under the United Evangelical Church in Hunan province
  - L, 1919-1966 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - To Welches from Herman Lambert, 1917 Apr-1920 Nov (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - To Welches from Emma and Horace Lequear, 1921 Jan-1925 Aug (Box 2, Folder 54)
    The Lequears were missionaries under the Reformed Church in Hunan province
  - To Welches from Algie and Mabel Lehman, 1920 Dec-1926 Nov (Box 2, Folder 55)
    The Lehmans were missionaries under the United Evangelical Church in Hunan
  - To Welches from Ralph Li-hsiao, 1922 Apr-1926 Jun (Box 3, Folder 56)
    Ralph Li-hsiao was a student supported by the Welches in Yuhsien; he addresses them as "mother and father."
  - M, 1918-1970 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - To Welches from B.H., B.E. and Alice Niebels, 1918 Aug-1924 Mar (Box 3, Folder 58)
    B.E. Niebels was a medical doctor at the United Evangelical MIssion Hospital in Lilung, Hunan province
  - To Lottie from Mabel Petersen, a friend in Illinois, 1919 Feb-1922 Sep (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - To Lottie from Mattie Peterson, 1920 Mar-1922 May (Box 3, Folder 60)
    Mattie Peterson was a missionary serving under the American Free Methodist Mission in Honan province. This correspondence refers to funds being paid by the Welches to the mission.
  - To Welches from Ida Rice, 1914 Nov-1916 Jan (Box 3, Folder 61)
    Ida Rice, a missionary in Inhambane, East Africa was encouraging the Welches to come serve in Africa.
  - To Welches from Daisy and M.E. Ritzman, 1919 Dec-1921 Oct (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - To Lottie from Effie and Emmeline Root, friends in Illinois, 1914(?)-1925 Nov (Box 3, Folder 63-64)
  - To Welches from Arthur and Molly Sanders, 1920 Jan-1925 Feb (Box 3, Folder 65)
    The Sanders were missionaries under the Evangelical Mission in Changsha
  - To Lottie from Ignatia Schoch, 1923 Oct-1925 Feb (Box 3, Folder 66)
    Ignatia Schoch was a missionary under the Evangelical Mission in Changsha
  - To the Welches from the Shambaugh family, 1918 Aug-1965 Dec (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - To Welches from Edward and Ruth Shelton, 1920 Dec-1926 Jun (Box 3, Folder 68)
    Includes news re. the Kuling Estate
  - To Welches from Rachel and S.M. Short, 1924 Jun-1934 Jun (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - To Lottie from Grace Somerville, 1922 Jun-1933 Jul (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - To Welches from Ralph Spreng, 1922 Dec-1924 Nov (Box 3, Folder 71)
    Ralph Spreng was a medical doctor at the Emma Dubs Memorial Hospital in Yuhsien
  - To Rolland from Mary Stone, 1919 Aug (Box 3, Folder 72)
    Written from Shanghai, this letter concerns Dr. Welch's request for a graduate nurse. Mary Stone was a medical doctor at Danforth Memorial Hospital.
  - To Lottie from Elvina Strunk, 1920 Jan-Nov (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - To the Welches from Theodore and Esther Suhr, 1921 Feb-1925 Jun (Box 3, Folder 73)
    The Suhrs were missionaries serving under the Evangelical Church in Liling, Hunan province. According to a letter written by Theodore Suhr in May, 1924 the Welches were asked to resign by the Board of Missions. Colleagues on the field were surprised by this action.
  - To the Welches from C.C. and Carrie Talbott, 1918 Sep-1959 Sep (Box 3, Folder 74-75)
    The Talbotts were missionaries under the United Evangelical Church in Yuhsien. Letters from C.C. Talbott refer to tensions between Rolland Welch and Dr. Dubs, Superintendent of the China mission.
  - To Lottie from Elizabeth Teeter, a friend in Illinois, 1918 Aug-1926 Dec (Box 3, Folder 76-77)
  - To/ from the Van Antwerps, 1918 Nov-1919 Mar (Box 4, Folder 78)
    Includes descriptive letter written by Lottie from Nanking
  - To Welches from H.E. and Sadie Voss, 1921 Jun-1927 Feb (Box 4, Folder 79)
    The Vosses were missionaries under the Evangelical Church in Yuhsien. Their letters refer to anti-Christian protests and unrest in the area.
  - W, 1922, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 80)
- Biographical Documentation, 1917-1923; Series III
  - Journal written by Rolland Welch during his trip from Chicago to Liling, China, 1917 Apr-Jun (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Biographical sketch re. Lottie Belle McClain and Rolland A. Welch prepared by their daughter, Mabel Welch Schroeder (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Articles re. Welches in Missionary Tidings; newspaper clippings; program from farewell service for Dr. R. A. Welch, 1917 Apr-May (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Certification of Mrs. R. A. Welch as missionary of United Evangelical Church, 1918 Aug (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Small diary of Lottie recording her daily activities in China, ca. 1921 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Documentation regarding loan from Board of Education of Free Methodist Church and insurance policy, 1907,1920 (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - School records from Kuling American School and biographical anecdote regarding Mabel Welch (daughter), 1922-1923 (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Diplomas of Lottie McClain Welch, 1917, 1918 (Box Ov2)
- Photographs and Lantern Slides, 1917-1923; Series IV
  - Printouts of scans of photographs from albums compiled by donor (originals returned): including portraits of Rolland, Lottie, and Mabel Welch, Welch extended familiy, the United Evangelical Mission compound in Yuhsien; Emma Dubs Memorial Hospital staff, American School in Kuling, scenes and colleagues, ca. 1917-1923 (Box 4, Folder 86)
  - Photographs of missionary colleagues, including C. Newton Dubs, head of the mission, ca. 1917-1923 (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - Photographs of Kuling, ca. 1917-1923 (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - Photographs of Peking and the Great Wall, ca. 1920 (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - Photographs of Chinese students and colleagues, ca. 1917-1923 (Box 4, Folder 90-91)
  - Photographs of damage from Japanese earthquake, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - Set of 84 glass lantern slides: people and scenes from the Welch's time in China, ca. 1917-1923 (Box Ov1)
  - Handmade photograph album: "China as seen from 1917-1923 by Dr. Rolland Welch"; two placards of mounted photographs; oversize photograph of mission conference (Box Ov2)
- Collected material and memorabilia, 1900-1947, n.d.; Series V
  - Articles, map, and clippings re. mission in Hunan, including Eleventh Annual Report of The Evangelical Hospital, Liling, Hunan (1926), 1924-1947 (Box 4, Folder 93)
  - Postcards, poems, programs, menus, receipts, clippings, 1917-1921, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 94)
  - Tribute banner with "love" character in Chinese, 1923 (Box Ov2)
  - Books and pamphlets, 1900-1925 (Box Ov2)
    A Mandarin Primer (1919); Analytical Chinese-English dictionary (1900); Chinese language books; announcement of The Kuling School (1921-1922); Hallock's Almanac (1923, 1925); The Linguist (1922); Things Seen in China (Chitty); Evangelical Missions (by Niebel and Dubs, 1919). Two additional books were added to the library's cataloged collection: Footprints on the Sands of China (Grace Cowles Story) and Adventures of a Sower (Minnie Dubs).
  - Diplomas: Rolland Welch's medical degree diploma from the University of Illinois (1915); Lottie Welch's diplomas from the Teachers' Training Board, Free Methodist Church (1917) and Greenville College Preparatory School (1918) (Box OV3)